<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>Brand safety</:h1>
<:p>Brand safety is a set of measures that aim to protect the image and reputation of brands from the negative or damaging influence of questionable or inappropriate content when advertising online. </:p>
<:p>With the move towards digital marketing, and specifically programmatic advertising, brand safety has become a growing concern for marketers and advertisers, and its importance has increased. Major brands have responded by cutting advertising budgets and pulling their ads off online advertising and social media platforms after finding their ads were placed next to undesirable content. </:p>
<:p>The global digital advertising industry considers the "Dirty Dozen" categories to avoid. The Interactive Advertising Bureau (IAB) added a 13th category: fake news.</:p>
<:p>1. Military conflict</:p>
<:p>2. Obscenity.</:p>
<:p>3. Drugs</:p>
<:p>4. Tobacco</:p>
<:p>5. Adult</:p>
<:p>6. Arms</:p>
<:p>7. Crime</:p>
<:p>8. Death/injury</:p>
<:p>9. Online piracy</:p>
<:p>10. Hate speech</:p>
<:p>11. Terrorism</:p>
<:p>12. Spam/harmful sites</:p>
<:p>13. Fake news</:p>
<:p>While these categories represent common risky environments, it is important for every brand to define what is considered unsafe for them. Airlines, for example, might not want their ads to appear next to breaking news about a plane crash.</:p>
<:p>To ensure brand safety, advertisers can opt for buying ad space directly from trusted publishers. This allows advertisers and publishers to work through the brand safety concerns and to pursue direct recourse when the agreement is not enforced. Advertisers and publishers may also employ third-party vendors of brand safety solutions that can be integrated into the advertising system. Other common preventive measures are black-lists of unsafe sites to avoid, or a white-lists of safe sites for advertising . The ads.txt (Authorized Digital Sellers) initiative from the IAB is designed to allow online media buyers to check the validity of the sellers from whom they buy.</:p>
<:p>- Reputation management</:p>