<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>Chronology of Shakespeare's plays</:h1>
<:p>This article presents a possible chronological listing of the composition of the plays of William Shakespeare.</:p>
<:p>Shakespearean scholars, beginning with Edmond Malone in 1778, have attempted to reconstruct the relative chronology of Shakespeare's "oeuvre" by various means, using external evidence (such as references to the plays by Shakespeare's contemporaries in both critical material and private documents, allusions in other plays, entries in the Stationers' Register, and records of performance and publication), and internal evidence (allusions within the plays to contemporary events, composition and publication dates of sources used by Shakespeare, stylistic analysis looking at the development of his style and diction over time, and the plays' context in the contemporary theatrical and literary "milieu"). Most modern chronologies are based on the work of E.K. Chambers in "The Problem of Chronology" (1930), published in his book "William Shakespeare: A Study of Facts and Problems, Vol. I".</:p>
<:p>Since the surviving evidence is fragmentary, there is not, nor can there be, a definitive or precise chronology. Performance history is often of limited use, as the first recorded performance of many plays was not necessarily when that play was first performed. For example, the first recorded performance of "Romeo and Juliet" was not until 1662, yet we know the play was performed in Shakespeare's lifetime. Thus, performance history reveals little about the date of composition.</:p>
<:p>Similarly, dates of first publication are often relatively useless in determining a chronology, as roughly half the plays were not published until seven years after Shakespeare's death, in the "First Folio" (1623), prepared by John Heminges and Henry Condell, and published by Edward Blount, William Jaggard and Isaac Jaggard. Performance dates and publication dates are also problematic insofar as many of the plays were performed several years before they were published. For example, "Titus Andronicus" was performed in 1592, but not published until 1594, "Othello" was performed in 1604 but not published until 1622, "King Lear" was performed in 1606 but not published until 1608. Performance and publication dates can thus be used only to determine terminal dates of composition, with the initial dates often remaining much more speculative.</:p>
<:p>In addition, some scholars dissent from the conventional dating system altogether. A notable scholar to do so is E. A. J. Honigmann, who has attempted to push back the beginning of Shakespeare's career four or five years to the mid-1580s, with his "early start" theory. Honigmann argues that Shakespeare began his career with "Titus Andronicus" in 1586 (the conventional school of thought is that Shakespeare began writing plays upon arriving in London "c."1590). Most scholars, however, adhere to a more orthodox chronology, and some, such as Gary Taylor and Sidney Thomas, argue that the early start theory causes more problems than it solves.</:p>
<:p>The chronology presented by E.K. Chambers in 1930 is as follows:</:p>
<:p>- "Henry VI, Part 2" (1590–1591)</:p>
<:p>- "Henry VI, Part 3" (1590–1591)</:p>
<:p>- "Henry VI, Part 1" (1591–1592)</:p>
<:p>- "Richard III" (1592–1593)</:p>
<:p>- "The Comedy of Errors" (1592–1593)</:p>
<:p>- "Titus Andronicus" (1593–1594)</:p>
<:p>- "The Taming of the Shrew" (1593–1594)</:p>
<:p>- "The Two Gentlemen of Verona" (1594–1595)</:p>
<:p>- "Love's Labour's Lost" (1594–1595)</:p>
<:p>- "Romeo and Juliet" (1594–1595)</:p>
<:p>- "Richard II" (1595–1596)</:p>
<:p>- "A Midsummer Night's Dream" (1595–1596)</:p>
<:p>- "King John" (1596–1597)</:p>
<:p>- "The Merchant of Venice" (1596–1597)</:p>
<:p>- "Henry IV, Part 1" (1597–1598)</:p>
<:p>- "Henry IV, Part 2" (1597–1598)</:p>
<:p>- "Much Ado About Nothing" (1598–1599)</:p>
<:p>- "Henry V" (1598–1599)</:p>
<:p>- "Julius Caesar" (1599–1600)</:p>
<:p>- "As You Like It" (1599–1600)</:p>
<:p>- "Twelfth Night" (1599–1600)</:p>
<:p>- "Hamlet" (1600–1601)</:p>
<:p>- "The Merry Wives of Windsor" (1600–1601)</:p>
<:p>- "Troilus and Cressida" (1601–1602)</:p>
<:p>- "All's Well That Ends Well" (1602–1603)</:p>
<:p>- "Measure for Measure" (1604–1605)</:p>
<:p>- "Othello" (1604–1605)</:p>
<:p>- "King Lear" (1605–1606)</:p>
<:p>- "Macbeth" (1605–1606)</:p>
<:p>- "Antony and Cleopatra" (1606–1607)</:p>
<:p>- "Coriolanus" (1607–1608)</:p>
<:p>- "Timon of Athens" (1607–1608)</:p>
<:p>- "Pericles, Prince of Tyre" (1608–1609)</:p>
<:p>- "Cymbeline" (1609–1610)</:p>
<:p>- "The Winter's Tale" (1610–1611)</:p>
<:p>- "The Tempest" (1611–1612)</:p>
<:p>- "Henry VIII" (1612–1613)</:p>
<:p>- "The Two Noble Kinsmen" (1612–1613)</:p>
<:p>There are six major modern scholarly editions of the "Complete Works of Shakespeare": </:p>
<:p>- "The Riverside Shakespeare" (edited by G. Blakemore Evans in 1974, with a second edition in 1996)</:p>
<:p>- "The Oxford Shakespeare: The Complete Works" (edited by Stanley Wells, Gary Taylor, John Jowett and William Montgomery in 1986, with a second edition in 2005)</:p>
<:p>- "The Norton Shakespeare: Based on the Oxford Edition" (edited by Stephen Greenblatt, Walter Cohen, Jean E. Howard and Katharine Eisaman Maus in 1997, with a second edition in 2008)</:p>
<:p>- "The Arden Shakespeare: Complete Works" (edited by Richard Proudfoot, Ann Thompson and David Scott Kastan in 1998, with a second edition in 2002 and a third in 2011)</:p>
<:p>- "The Complete Pelican Shakespeare" (edited by Stephen Orgel and A. R. Braunmuller in 2002), and</:p>
<:p>- "The RSC Shakespeare: Complete Works" (edited by Jonathan Bate and Eric Rasmussen in 2007).</:p>
<:p>Additionally, as with Oxford, Arden, Pelican and the RSC, the New Cambridge Shakespeare, the New Penguin Shakespeare, the Signet Classic Shakespeare, the Dover Wilson Shakespeare, the Shakespeare Folios and the Folger Shakespeare Library all publish scholarly editions of individual plays, although none have issued a complete works volume.</:p>
<:p>"Arden" presents the plays alphabetically without any attempt to construct an overall chronology. "Oxford", "Riverside", "Norton" and "RSC" all present chronologies which differ from one another and which attempt to construct only approximate dating. The following list is based on that of "The Oxford Shakespeare: The Complete Works" (2nd ed.) and the accompanying "William Shakespeare: A Textual Companion" (Revised ed.), edited by Stanley Wells and Gary Taylor. However, none of the major chronologies has any real authority over any of the others.</:p>
<:p>- Internet Shakespeare Editions</:p>
<:p>- "Narrative and Dramatic Sources of all Shakespeare's works" ()</:p>
<:p>- "Shakespeare's Works: A Timeline" ()</:p>
<:p>- "The Chronology of Shakespeare's Plays" ()</:p>
<:p>- "The Collected Works of William Shakespeare Arranged Chronologically" ()</:p>