<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>Global Internet usage</:h1>
<:p>Global Internet usage refers to the number of people who use the Internet worldwide, which can be displayed using tables, charts, maps and articles which contain more detailed information on a wide range of usage measures.</:p>
<:p>As of April 2019, 56.1% of the world's population has internet access, and 81% of the developed world. In 2015, the International Telecommunication Union estimated about 3.2 billion people, or almost half of the world's population, would be online by the end of the year. Of them, about 2 billion would be from developing countries, including 89 million from least developed countries.</:p>
<:p>The Web Index is a composite statistic designed and produced by the World Wide Web Foundation. It provides a multi-dimensional measure of the World Wide Web’s contribution to development and human rights globally. It covers 86 countries as of 2014, the latest year for which the index has been compiled. It incorporates indicators that assess the areas of universal access, freedom and openness, relevant content, and empowerment, which indicate economic, social, and political impacts of the Web.</:p>
<:p>The Carna Botnet was a botnet of 420,000 devices created by hackers to measure the extent of the Internet in what the creators called the "Internet Census of 2012". </:p>
<:p>- Digital rights</:p>
<:p>- Fiber to the premises by country</:p>
<:p>- Internet access</:p>
<:p>- Internet traffic</:p>
<:p>- List of countries by Internet connection speeds</:p>
<:p>- List of countries by number of mobile phones in use</:p>
<:p>- List of social networking websites</:p>
<:p>- Zettabyte Era</:p>
<:p>- "ICT Data and Statistics", International Telecommunications Union (ITU).</:p>
<:p>- Internet Live Stats, Real Time Statistics Project.</:p>
<:p>- Internet World Stats: Usage and Population Statistics, Miniwatts Marketing Group.</:p>
<:p>- "40 maps that explain the internet", Timothy B. Lee, Vox Media, 2 June 2014.</:p>
<:p>- "Information Geographies", Oxford Internet Institute.</:p>
<:p>- "Internet Monitor", a research project of the Berkman Center for Internet & Society at Harvard University to evaluate, describe, and summarize the means, mechanisms, and extent of Internet access, content controls and activity around the world.</:p>