<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>Hebenon</:h1>
<:p>Hebenon (or hebona) is a botanical substance described in William Shakespeare's tragic play "Hamlet". The identity and nature of the poison has been a source of speculation for centuries.</:p>
<:p>Hebenon is the agent of death in Hamlet's father's murder, it sets in motion the events of the play. It is spelled "hebona" in the Quartos and "hebenon" in the Folios. This is the only mention of "hebenon/hebona" in any of Shakespeare's plays.</:p>
<:p>Writers from Shakespeare's time to the present have speculated about the identity of hebenon.</:p>
<:p>It may be different from hemlock, as hemlock is explicitly mentioned in several other writings of his. In favor of it being yew are the familiarity of yew as a poison and the similarity in symptoms. Edmund Spenser wrote of "the deadly heben bow" ("heben" being a word for ebony, from Latin "hebenus"). In favor of ebony (specifically, guaiac) is the fact that ebony was sometimes written with an h, but arguing against it is the low toxicity of guaiac. In favour of henbane is its toxic nature and the possible origin of hebenon as metathesis from henbane. Other authors question whether there is sufficient evidence to resolve the issue, or even whether Shakespeare's attention to botany and pharmacology was sufficient to say he meant a specific plant.</:p>
<:p>Hebenon is a poison used to kill a pope and other world leaders in the thriller "The Tao Deception" by John M Green.</:p>
<:p>Further reading</:p>
<:p>- Huxtable, Ryan J. "On the nature of Shakespeare's cursed hebona." "Perspectives in Biology and Medicine" Winter 1993: 262+. "Academic OneFile". 10 Oct. 2012.</:p>
<:p>- G. H. "Shakespeare's Hebona" "Pharmacy in History" Vol. 35, No. 3 (1993), p. 137 DOI: 10.2307/41111539</:p>
<:p>- Harrison, Jr., Thomas P. "Shakespeare's 'Hebenon' Again" "The Modern Language Review" Vol. 40, No. 4, Oct., 1945 p. 310-311</:p>
<:p>- Montgomery, Marshall. ""Cursed Hebenon" (Or "Hebona")" "The Modern Language Review" Vol. 15, No. 3, Jul., 1920 p. 304-306</:p>
<:p>- Simpson, R. R. "Shakespeare on the Ear, Nose and Throat" "The Journal of Laryngology & Otology" Volume64 Issue06 June 1950, pp 342–352</:p>
<:p>- Tabor, Edward. "Plant poisons in Shakespeare" "Economic Botany" 1970, Volume 24, Number 1, Pages 81–94</:p>
<:p>- by K.N. Rao, Professor of Botany in Chennai, India</:p>