<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>History of communication</:h1>
<:p>Since primitive times, significant changes in communication technologies (media and appropriate inscription tools) have evolved in tandem with shifts in political and economic systems, and by extension, systems of power. Communication can range from very subtle processes of exchange, to full conversations and mass communication. Human communication was revolutionized with the origin of speech approximately 500,000 BCE. Symbols were developed about 30,000 years ago. The imperfection of speech, which nonetheless allowed easier dissemination of ideas and eventually resulted in the creation of new forms of communications, improving both the range at which people could communicate and the longevity of the information. All of those inventions were based on the key concept of the symbol.</:p>
<:p>The oldest known symbols created for the purpose of communication were cave paintings, a form of rock art, dating to the Upper Paleolithic age. The oldest known cave painting is located within Chauvet Cave, dated to around 30,000 BC. These paintings contained increasing amounts of information: people may have created the first calendar as far back as 15,000 years ago. The connection between drawing and writing is further shown by linguistics: in Ancient Egypt and Ancient Greece the concepts and words of drawing and writing were one and the same (Egyptian: 's-sh', Greek: 'graphein').</:p>
<:p>The next advancement in the history of communications came with the production of petroglyphs, carvings into a rock surface. It took about 20,000 years for homo sapiens to move from the first cave paintings to the first petroglyphs, which are dated to approximately the Neolithic and late Upper Paleolithic boundary, about 10,000 to 12,000 years ago.</:p>
<:p>It is possible that Homo sapiens of that time used some other forms of communication, often for mnemonic purposes - specially arranged stones, symbols carved in wood or earth, quipu-like ropes, tattoos, but little other than the most durable carved stones has survived to modern times and we can only speculate about their existence based on our observation of still existing 'hunter-gatherer' cultures such as those of Africa or Oceania.</:p>
<:p>A pictogram (pictograph) is a symbol representing a concept, object, activity, place or event by illustration. Pictography is a form of proto-writing whereby ideas are transmitted through drawing. Pictographs were the next step in the evolution of communication: the most important difference between petroglyphs and pictograms is that petroglyphs are simply showing an event, but</:p>
<:p>pictograms are telling a story about the event, thus they can for example be ordered chronologically.</:p>
<:p>Pictograms were used by various ancient cultures all over the world since around 9000 BC, when tokens marked with simple pictures began to be used to label basic farm produce, and become increasingly popular around 6000–5000 BC.</:p>
<:p>They were the basis of cuneiform and hieroglyphs, and began to develop into logographic writing systems around 5000 BC.</:p>
<:p>Pictograms, in turn, evolved into ideograms, graphical symbols that represent an idea. Their ancestors, the pictograms, could represent only something resembling their form: therefore a pictogram of a circle could represent a sun, but not concepts like 'heat', 'light', 'day' or 'Great God of the Sun'. Ideograms, on the other hand, could convey more abstract concepts, so that for example an ideogram of two sticks can mean not only 'legs' but also a verb 'to walk'.</:p>
<:p>Because some ideas are universal, many different cultures developed similar ideograms. For example, an eye with a tear means 'sadness' in Native American ideograms in California, as it does for the Aztecs, the early Chinese and the Egyptians. </:p>
<:p>Ideograms were precursors of logographic writing systems such as Egyptian hieroglyphs and Chinese characters. </:p>
<:p>Examples of ideographical proto-writing systems, thought not to contain language-specific information, include the Vinca script (see also Tărtăria tablets) and the early Indus script. In both cases there are claims of decipherment of linguistic content, without wide acceptance. </:p>
<:p>The oldest-known forms of writing were primarily logographic in nature, based on pictographic and ideographic elements. Most writing systems can be broadly divided into three categories: "logographic", "syllabic" and "alphabetic" (or "segmental"); however, all three may be found in any given writing system in varying proportions, often making it difficult to categorise a system uniquely.</:p>
<:p>The invention of the first writing systems is roughly contemporary with the beginning of the Bronze Age in the late Neolithic of the late 4000 BC. The first writing system is generally believed to have been invented in pre-historic Sumer and developed by the late 3000's BC into cuneiform. Egyptian hieroglyphs, and the undeciphered Proto-Elamite writing system and Indus Valley script also date to this era, though a few scholars have questioned the Indus Valley script's status as a writing system.</:p>
<:p>The original Sumerian writing system was derived from a system of clay tokens used to represent commodities. By the end of the 4th millennium BC, this had evolved into a method of keeping accounts, using a round-shaped stylus impressed into soft clay at different angles for recording numbers. This was gradually augmented with pictographic writing using a sharp stylus to indicate what was being counted. Round-stylus and sharp-stylus writing was gradually replaced about 2700–2000 BC by writing using a wedge-shaped stylus (hence the term cuneiform), at first only for logograms, but developed to include phonetic elements by the 2800 BC. About 2600 BC cuneiform began to represent syllables of spoken Sumerian language.</:p>
<:p>Finally, cuneiform writing became a general purpose writing system for logograms, syllables, and numbers. By the 26th century BC, this script had been adapted to another Mesopotamian language, Akkadian, and from there to others such as Hurrian, and Hittite. Scripts similar in appearance to this writing system include those for Ugaritic and Old Persian.</:p>
<:p>The Chinese script may have originated independently of the Middle Eastern scripts, around the 16th century BC (early Shang Dynasty), out of a late neolithic Chinese system of proto-writing dating back to c. 6000 BC. The pre-Columbian writing systems of the Americas, including Olmec and Mayan, are also generally believed to have had independent origins.</:p>
<:p>The first pure alphabets (properly, "abjads", mapping single symbols to single phonemes, but not necessarily each phoneme to a symbol) emerged around 2000 BC in Ancient Egypt, but by then alphabetic principles had already been incorporated into Egyptian hieroglyphs for a millennium (see Middle Bronze Age alphabets).</:p>
<:p>By 2700 BC, Egyptian writing had a set of some 22 hieroglyphs to represent syllables that begin with a single consonant of their language, plus a vowel (or no vowel) to be supplied by the native speaker. These glyphs were used as pronunciation guides for logograms, to write grammatical inflections, and, later, to transcribe loan words and foreign names.</:p>
<:p>However, although seemingly alphabetic in nature, the original Egyptian uniliterals were not a system and were never used by themselves to encode Egyptian speech. In the Middle Bronze Age an apparently "alphabetic" system is thought by some to have been developed in central Egypt around 1700 BC for or by Semitic workers, but we cannot read these early writings and their exact nature remains open to interpretation.</:p>
<:p>Over the next five centuries this Semitic "alphabet" (really a syllabary like Phoenician writing) seems to have spread north. All subsequent alphabets around the world with the sole exception of Korean Hangul have either descended from it, or been inspired by one of its descendants.</:p>
<:p>- 30,000 BC – In ice-age Europe, people mark ivory, bone, and stone with patterns to keep track of time, using a lunar calendar.</:p>
<:p>- 14,000 BC – In what is now Mezhirich, Ukraine, the first known artifact with a map on it is made using bone.</:p>
<:p>- Prior to 3500 BC – Communication was carried out through paintings of indigenous tribes.</:p>
<:p>- 3500s BC – The Sumerians develop cuneiform writing and the Egyptians develop hieroglyphic writing.</:p>
<:p>- 16th century BC – The Phoenicians develop an alphabet.</:p>
<:p>- 105 – Tsai Lun invents paper.</:p>
<:p>- 7th century – Hindu-Malayan empires write legal documents on copper plate scrolls, and write other documents on more perishable media.</:p>
<:p>- 751 – Paper is introduced to the Muslim world after the Battle of Talas.</:p>
<:p>- 1250 – The quill is used for writing.</:p>
<:p>- 1305 – The Chinese develop wooden block movable type printing.</:p>
<:p>- 1450 – Johannes Gutenberg invents a printing press with metal movable type.</:p>
<:p>- 1844 – Charles Fenerty produces paper from a wood pulp, eliminating rag paper which was in limited supply.</:p>
<:p>- 1849 – Associated Press organizes Nova Scotia pony express to carry latest European news for New York newspapers.</:p>
<:p>- 1958 – Chester Carlson presents the first photocopier suitable for office use.</:p>
<:p>The history of telecommunication - the transmission of signals over a distance for the purpose of communication - began thousands of years ago with the use of smoke signals and drums in Africa, America and parts of Asia. In the 1790s the first fixed semaphore systems emerged in Europe however it was not until the 1830s that electrical telecommunication systems started to appear.</:p>
<:p>- AD 26–37 – Roman Emperor Tiberius rules the empire from the island of Capri by signaling messages with metal mirrors to reflect the sun.</:p>
<:p>- 1520 – Ships on Ferdinand Magellan's voyage signal to each other by firing cannon and raising flags.</:p>
<:p>- 1792 – Claude Chappe establishes the first long-distance semaphore telegraph line.</:p>
<:p>- 1831 – Joseph Henry proposes and builds an electric telegraph.</:p>
<:p>- 1836 – Samuel Morse develops the Morse code.</:p>
<:p>- 1843 – Samuel Morse builds the first long distance electric telegraph line.</:p>
<:p>- 1876 – Alexander Graham Bell and Thomas A. Watson exhibit an electric telephone in Boston.</:p>
<:p>- 1889 – Almon Strowger patents the direct dial</:p>
<:p>- 1877 – Thomas Edison patents the phonograph.</:p>
<:p>- 1920 – Radio station KDKA based in Pittsburgh began the first broadcast.</:p>
<:p>- 1925 – John Logie Baird transmits the first television signal.</:p>
<:p>- 1942 – Hedy Lamarr and George Antheil invent frequency hopping spread spectrum communication technique.</:p>
<:p>- 1947 – Full-scale commercial television is first broadcast.</:p>
<:p>- 1963 – First geosynchronous communications satellite is launched, 17.5 years after Arthur C. Clarke's article.</:p>
<:p>- 1999 – Sirius satellite radio is introduced.</:p>
<:p>- 1843 – Patent issued for the "Electric Printing Telegraph", a very early forerunner of the fax machine</:p>
<:p>- 1926 – Commercial availability of the radiofax</:p>
<:p>- 1964 – First modern fax machine commercially available (Long Distance Xerography)</:p>
<:p>- 1947 – Douglas H. Ring and W. Rae Young of Bell Labs propose a cell-based approach which led to "cellular phones."</:p>
<:p>- 1981 – Nordic Mobile Telephone, the world's first automatic mobile phone is put into operation</:p>
<:p>- 1991 – GSM is put into operation</:p>
<:p>- 1992 – Neil Papworth sends the first SMS (or text message).</:p>
<:p>- 1999 – 45% of Australians have a mobile phone.</:p>
<:p>- 1949 – Claude Elwood Shannon, the "father of information theory", mathematically proves the Nyquist–Shannon sampling theorem.</:p>
<:p>- 1965 – First email sent (at MIT).</:p>
<:p>- 1966 – Charles Kao realizes that silica-based optical waveguides offer a practical way to transmit light via total internal reflection.</:p>
<:p>- 1969 – The first hosts of ARPANET, Internet's ancestor, are connected.</:p>
<:p>- 1971 – Erna Schneider Hoover invent a computerized switching system for telephone traffic.</:p>
<:p>- 1971 – 8-inch floppy disk removable storage medium for computers is introduced.</:p>
<:p>- 1975 – "First list servers are introduced."</:p>
<:p>- 1976 – The personal computer (PC) market is born.</:p>
<:p>- 1977 – Donald Knuth begins work on TeX.</:p>
<:p>- 1981 – Hayes Smartmodem introduced.</:p>
<:p>- 1983 – Microsoft Word software is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 1985 - AOL is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 1989 – Tim Berners-Lee and Robert Cailliau build the prototype system which became the World Wide Web at CERN.</:p>
<:p>- 1989 – WordPerfect 5.1 word processing software released.</:p>
<:p>- 1991 – Anders Olsson transmits solitary waves through an optical fiber with a data rate of 32 billion bits per second.</:p>
<:p>- 1992 – Internet2 organization is created.</:p>
<:p>- 1992 – IBM ThinkPad 700C laptop computer created. It was lightweight compared to its predecessors.</:p>
<:p>- 1993 – Mosaic graphical web browser is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 1994 – Internet radio broadcasting is born.</:p>
<:p>- 1996 – Motorola StarTAC mobile phone introduced. It was significantly smaller than previous cellphones.</:p>
<:p>- 1997 – SixDegrees.com is launched, the first of a number of early social networking services</:p>
<:p>- 1998 – Lotus Notes software is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 1999 – Napster peer-to-peer file sharing is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 2001 – Cyworld adds social networking features and becomes the first of a number of mass-market social networking service</:p>
<:p>- 2003 – Skype video calling software is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 2004 – Facebook is launched, becoming the largest social networking site in 2009.</:p>
<:p>- 2005 – YouTube, the video sharing site, is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 2006 – Twitter is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 2007 – iPhone is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 2009 – Whatsapp is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 2010 – Instagram is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 2011 – Snapchat is launched.</:p>
<:p>- 2015 – Discord is launched.</:p>
<:p>- List of years in home video</:p>
<:p>- Timeline of photography technology</:p>
<:p>- Historical linguistics</:p>
<:p>- Babylonokia (art piece featuring a cuneiform mobile phone keyboard)</:p>
<:p>- Piotr Konieczny, Komunikacja: od mowy do Internetu, "Histmag #49"</:p>
<:p>- Asante, Molefi Kete, Yoshitaka Miike, and Jing Yin, eds. "The global intercultural communication reader" (Routledge, 2014)</:p>
<:p>- Berger, Arthur Asa. "Media and communication research methods: An introduction to qualitative and quantitative approaches" (SAGE 2013)</:p>
<:p>- Burke, Peter. "A Social History of Knowledge: From Gutenberg to Diderot" (2000)</:p>
<:p>- Burke, Peter. " A Social History of Knowledge II: From the Encyclopaedia to Wikipedia" (2012)</:p>
<:p>- de Mooij, Marieke. "Theories of Mass Communication and Media Effects Across Cultures." in "Human and Mediated Communication around the World" (Springer 2014) pp 355–393.</:p>
<:p>- Esser, Frank, and Thomas Hanitzsch, eds. "The handbook of comparative communication research" (Routledge, 2012)</:p>
<:p>- Jensen, Klaus Bruhn, ed. "A handbook of media and communication research: qualitative and quantitative methodologies" (Routledge, 2013)</:p>
<:p>- Paxson, Peyton. "Mass Communications and Media Studies: An Introduction" (Bloomsbury, 2010)</:p>
<:p>- Poe, Marshall T. "A History of Communications: Media and Society From the Evolution of Speech to the Internet" (Cambridge University Press; 2011) 352 pages; Documents how successive forms of communication are embraced and, in turn, foment change in social institutions.</:p>
<:p>- Schramm, Wilbur. " Mass Communications" (1963)</:p>
<:p>- Schramm, Wilbur, ed. " Mass Communications: A Reader" (1960)</:p>
<:p>- Simonson, Peter. "Refiguring Mass Communication: A History" (2010)</:p>