<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>List of accolades received by Netflix</:h1>
<:p>Netflix is an American on-demand internet streaming media provider. The company founded by Reed Hastings and Marc Randolph on August 29, 1997, in Scotts Valley, California. It specializes in and provides streaming media and video-on-demand online and DVD by mail. In 2013, Netflix expanded into film and television production, as well as online distribution.</:p>
<:p>Due to the release of original content and its reception, Netflix became a contender for major awards. On July 18, 2013, Netflix became the first streaming service to earned major nominations and eventually win a Primetime Emmy Award. Also "House of Cards" became the first online-only web television program to be nominated and its pilot episode, "Chapter 1", was the first webisode of a television series to win an Emmy.</:p>
<:p>On January 12, 2014, Netflix and Robin Wright ("House of Cards") made history at the Golden Globe Awards, by becoming the first streaming platform to be nominated and the first actress for a web television program to win the award, respectively. Netflix was also the first high profile streaming service to earned an Academy Award nomination. In addition, Netflix has earned accolades with different peers groups and associations, including: Television Critics Association Awards, BAFTA Awards, Critics' Choice Television Awards, Screen Actors Guild Awards and others.</:p>
<:p>In 2013, originals like "House of Cards" and "Orange Is the New Black" received critical acclaim from critics and viewers. As a result Netflix earned fourteen Primetime Emmy nominations for original online-only web television programs. "House of Cards"' pilot episode "Chapter 1" was awarded the Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Directing for a Drama Series, becoming the first webisode of a television series to win an Emmy. Other nominations included Outstanding Drama Series, Outstanding Lead Actor in a Drama Series (Kevin Spacey) and Outstanding Lead Actress in a Drama Series (Robin Wright). On December 11, 2013, Kevin Spacey ("House of Cards") and Jason Bateman ("Arrested Development") were the first actors nominated at the Screen Actor Guild Awards. Spacey for Outstanding Performance by a Female Actor in a Drama Series and Bateman for Outstanding Performance by a Male Actor in a Comedy Series The day after, the network earned six Golden Globe Award nominations, including Best Television Series – Drama. On January 12, 2014, Robin Wright ("House of Cards") won the Golden Globe Award for Best Actress – Television Series Drama for her portrayal of Claire Underwood. With the accolade, Wright became the first actress to win a Golden Globe for an online-only web television series. It was also Netflix's first award in an acting category. The company also received nominations for the Writers Guild of America Awards,</:p>
<:p>Directors Guild of America Awards and Grammy Awards.</:p>
<:p>On January 12, 2014, with "The Square", Netflix became the first high profile streaming service to be nominated for an Academy Award. On February, "Orange Is the New Black" dominated the Satellite Awards winning Best Television Series – Musical or Comedy, Best Actress – Television Series Musical or Comedy (Taylor Schilling), Best Supporting Actress – Series, Miniseries or Television Film (Laura Prepon) and Best Cast – Television Series. On the drama side, Robin Wright won for Best Actress – Television Series Drama. Later that year, "House of Cards" earned a British Academy Television Award nomination for Best International Programme and a Critics' Choice Television Award nomination for Best Actress in a Drama Series (Robin Wright). On July 10, 2014, nominations for the 66th Primetime Emmy Awards were announced, with Netflix scoring a total of thirty one. "Orange Is the New Black" earned a total of twelve nominations, including Outstanding Comedy Series, Outstanding Lead Actress in a Comedy Series (Taylor Schilling), Outstanding Supporting Actress in a Comedy Series (Kate Mulgrew), Outstanding Directing for a Comedy Series (Jodie Foster) and Outstanding Writing for a Comedy Series (Liz Friedman and Jenji Kohan). Nominated for Outstanding Guest Actress in a Comedy Series were Uzo Aduba, Laverne Cox and Natasha Lyonne. Uzo Aduba won the Emmy, becoming the first actress from a Netflix original to win the award. In Addition, Laverne Cox made history by becoming the first transgender person ever nominated for a Primetime Emmy Award. Meanwhile "Orange Is the New Black" debuted strong, "House of Cards" increased the number of nominations from nine to thirteen. The political drama held Outstanding Drama Series and both leads in acting. It debuted entries in categories like Outstanding Writing for a Drama Series (Beau Willimon), Outstanding Guest Actor in a Drama Series (Reg E. Cathey) and Outstanding Guest Actress in a Drama Series (Kate Mara).</:p>
<:p>At the 72nd Golden Globe Awards, Kevin Spacey won in the category Best Actor – Television Series Drama and became Netflix first actor to win the award. On January 15, 2015, Netflix earned its second Academy Award nomination with "Virunga" in the Documentary Feature category. Days later, Kevin Spacey and Uzo Aduba won at the 21st Screen Actors Guild Awards, for Outstanding Performance by a Male Actor in a Drama Series and Outstanding Performance by a Female Actor in a Comedy Series, respectively. Also "Orange Is the New Black" won the Screen Actors Guild Award for Outstanding Performance by an Ensemble in a Comedy Series. At the Producers Guild Awards, "Orange Is the New Black" won for Best Episodic Comedy and "House of Cards" was nominated for the second time. For the 2015 Primetime Emmy awards the company received thirty four nominations, with "House of Cards" and "Unbreakable Kimmy Schmidt" leading. Despite the critical acclaim of Season 2, "Orange Is the New Black" decreased in nominations, from twelve to four, as a result of switching from comedy to drama categories. Tina Fey's "Unbreakable Kimmy Schmidt" debuted with seven entries, "Bloodline" with two and "Grace and Frankie" with one. Uzo Aduba won her second consecutive Emmy, this time in the Outstanding Supporting Actress in a Drama Series category for the episode: "Hugs Can Be Deceiving".</:p>
<:p>On January 10, 2016, "Narcos" was nominated for two Golden Globe Awards, including Best Television Series – Drama and Best Actor – Television Series Drama for Wagner Moura. Days later, "Master of None" made its debut winning the Critics' Choice Television Award for Best Comedy Series. Uzo Aduba and the cast of "Orange Is the New Black" won a Screen Actors Guild for Outstanding Performance by a Female Actor in a Comedy Series and Outstanding Performance by an Ensemble in a Comedy Series, for a second consecutive time. Kevin Spacey repeated as the winner of the SAG Award for Outstanding Performance by a Male Actor in a Drama Series. For the 88th Academy Awards, "" and "What Happened, Miss Simone?" were nominated. "What Happened, Miss Simone?" was nominated for a Grammy Award for Best Music Film. For the third season of "Orange Is the New Black", Taylor Schilling won for the second time the Satellite Award for Best Actress – Television Series Musical or Comedy. For the 2016 Primetime Emmys, Netflix was the third company with most nominations with fifty four. Nominations lead by "House of Cards", "Making a Murderer", "What Happened, Miss Simone?" and "Master of None". "Making a Murderer" won for Outstanding Documentary or Nonfiction Series, Outstanding Directing for Nonfiction Programming and Outstanding Writing for Nonfiction Programming. Aziz Ansari and Alan Yang, from "Master of None" won the Emmy for writing the episode "Parents".</:p>
<:p>The Academy Awards, also known as the Oscars, is a set of twenty-four awards for artistic and technical merit in the American film industry, given annually by the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences (AMPAS), to recognize excellence in cinematic achievements as assessed by the Academy's voting membership. Netflix has won six awards from twenty nine nominations.</:p>
<:p>An Emmy Award, or simply Emmy, is an American award that recognizes excellence in the television industry, and corresponds to the Oscar (for film), the Tony Award (for theatre), and the Grammy Award (for music). Netflix has won thirty seven from one hundred twenty eight nominations. Below is a list of selected categories won by original programming.</:p>
<:p>A Grammy Award (originally called Gramophone Award), or Grammy, is an honor awarded by The Recording Academy to recognize outstanding achievement in the mainly English-language music industry. Netflix has been nominated four times.</:p>
<:p>Golden Globe Awards are accolades bestowed by the ninety three members of the Hollywood Foreign Press Association, recognizing excellence in film and television, both domestic and foreign. Netflix has received four Golden Globe Awards from twenty seven nominations.</:p>
<:p>Rotten Tomatoes is an American review aggregator website for film and television. The company was launched in August 1998 by Senh Duong and since January 2010 has been owned by Flixster, which was, in turn, acquired in 2011 by Warner Bros. Below are listed shows with multiple seasons with aggregate score.</:p>
<:p>Metacritic is a website that aggregates reviews of media products: music albums, video games, films, TV shows, and formerly, books. For each product, the scores from each review are averaged (a weighted average). Below are listed shows with multiple seasons with metascore. </:p>
<:p>- List of TCA Awards received by Netflix</:p>
<:p>- List of Critics' Choice Awards received by Netflix</:p>