<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>List of newsgroups</:h1>
<:p>This is a partial list of newsgroups that are significant for their popularity or their position in Usenet history.</:p>
<:p>These are the most widely distributed and carefully controlled newsgroup hierarchies. See Big 8 (Usenet) and the Great Renaming for more information.</:p>
<:p>Computer-related topics.</:p>
<:p>Topics related to the humanities (fine arts, literature, philosophy, Classical Latin, etc.).</:p>
<:p>Miscellaneous topics. Examples include:</:p>
<:p>- misc.legal.moderated — A moderated legal forum.</:p>
<:p>- "misc.taxes.moderated" — A moderated professional tax forum open to the general public.</:p>
<:p>Matters related to the functioning of Usenet itself. Examples include:</:p>
<:p>- "news.admin.net-abuse.blocklisting" — discussion related to the use of blocklists to deal with spam and other unwanted network traffic.</:p>
<:p>- "news.admin.net-abuse.email" — discussion of abuse of email by spammers and other parties.</:p>
<:p>Recreation and entertainment topics.</:p>
<:p>Examples include:</:p>
<:p>- "rec.arts.movies.current-films"—The latest movie releases.</:p>
<:p>- "rec.arts.movies.past-films"—Past films.</:p>
<:p>- "rec.arts.poems</:p>
<:p>- "rec.arts.sf.tv"—Discussing general television SF (i.e. science-fiction, or "speculative fiction").</:p>
<:p>- "rec.arts.sf.tv.babylon5.moderated"—discussion of "Babylon 5" and other projects of J. Michael Straczynski.</:p>
<:p>- "rec.arts.tv"—Television, its history, and past and current shows, i.e. the main television newsgroup.</:p>
<:p>- "rec.arts.tv.soaps.cbs"—discussion about soap operas broadcast by the CBS television network.</:p>
<:p>- "rec.arts.tv.mst3k.misc"—discussion of the TV series "Mystery Science Theater 3000".</:p>
<:p>- "rec.arts.tv.x-factor"—General discussion of the X-Factor tv show and all its worldwide editions.</:p>
<:p>- "rec.food.cooking"—"discussion of cooking in general. Recipes and requests for recipes are welcome here, as are discussions of cooking techniques, equipment, etc."</:p>
<:p>- "rec.humor.oracle"—Internet humor</:p>
<:p>- "rec.sport.cricket"—general discussion of world cricket.</:p>
<:p>- "rec.sport.soccer"—general discussion of world football (soccer).</:p>
<:p>- "rec.woodworking"—general discussion of woodworking.</:p>
<:p>Science-related topics.</:p>
<:p>- Sci.bio.*</:p>
<:p>- sci.bio.paleontology</:p>
<:p>- sci.bio.evolution</:p>
<:p>- sci.skeptic</:p>
<:p>Discussion related to society and social subcultures. Examples include:</:p>
<:p>- "soc.culture.usa"— for the discussion of culture in the USA.</:p>
<:p>- "soc.culture.iraq"— for the discussion of Iraq.</:p>
<:p>- "soc.genealogy"— for the discussion of genealogy.</:p>
<:p>- "soc.motss"— for the discussion of gay and lesbian issues.</:p>
<:p>- "soc.org.nonprofit"— for the discussion of nonprofit organization management issues.</:p>
<:p>- "soc.org.service—clubs.misc"— for the discussion of service clubs such as Kiwanis, Lions, Rotary International, Civitan International and Optimists.</:p>
<:p>- "soc.penpals"— to find penpals</:p>
<:p>- "soc.politics"— for the discussion of politics</:p>
<:p>- "soc.religion.bahai"— for the discussion of Bahai</:p>
<:p>- "soc.religion.christian"— for the discussion of Christianity</:p>
<:p>- "soc.rights-human"— for the discussion of human rights</:p>
<:p>Discussion of various topics, especially controversial ones. Includes political topics as well. Examples include:</:p>
<:p>- "talk.bizarre" — a newsgroup for experiencing the bizarre.</:p>
<:p>- "talk.origins" — evolution-creationism controversy which maintains an extensive FAQ.</:p>
<:p>This is the most extensive newsgroup hierarchy outside of the Big 8. Examples include:</:p>
<:p>- "alt.2600" — Official group for</:p>
<:p>- "Alt.Adoption" — for adoption</:p>
<:p>- "alt.arts.poetry.comments" — for poetry and poetry critique</:p>
<:p>- "alt.asian-movies" — for discussions focusing mainly on Hong Kong action cinema.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.atheism" — discusses atheism</:p>
<:p>- "alt.binaries.boneless"</:p>
<:p>- "alt.binaries.slack" — artwork created by and for the Church of the SubGenius.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.callahans" — Spider Robinson's Callahan's Place online</:p>
<:p>- "alt.config" — creation of new newsgroups in the "alt.*" hierarchy".</:p>
<:p>- "alt.digitiser" — discussion of the video games magazine "Digitiser".</:p>
<:p>- "alt.fan" — fandom discussions.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.gothic" — a gothic newsgroup and birthplace of Convergence</:p>
<:p>- "alt.horology" This Internet newsgroup concerns all aspects of horology (the science of time and timekeeping, clocks and watches). Those posting to it range from novices to collectors to professional watchmakers & clockmakers.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.religion.kibology" — He who Greps.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.sex" — the first "alt.*" newsgroup for discussion of sexual topics.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.sex.bondage" — discussion of BDSM sex.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.sex.cancel" — set up specifically as a means of defeating newsgroup spam cross-posted to the entire alt.sex hierarchy</:p>
<:p>- "alt.sex.stories" — text-based erotic stories of all types.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.slack" — Posting relating to the Church of the Subgenius.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.startrek.vs.starwars" — created to discuss the Comparison of Star Trek and Star Wars.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.suicide.holiday" — pro-choice discussion of suicide.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.sysadmin.recovery" — the Scary Devil Monastery.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.tasteless" — discussion of subject matter in too poor taste to be discussed elsewhere.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.tv.simpsons" — discusses the TV show "The Simpsons."</:p>
<:p>- "alt.usage.english" — discussion of English words, grammar, etymology</:p>
<:p>- "alt.usenet.kooks" — discussion of Usenet kooks and their idiosyncratic theories.</:p>
<:p>- "alt.zines" — discussion of small-press publications, magazines, and pamphlets (zines).</:p>
<:p>These newsgroups fall outside of the official Big 8 hierarchies, as well as the less formal "alt" hierarchy. Other newsgroups can consist of geographic regions (official or unofficial), corporations, and other institutions or groups.</:p>