<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>List of original programs distributed by Netflix</:h1>
<:p>Netflix is an American global on-demand Internet streaming media provider, that has distributed a number of original programs, including original series, specials (including stand-up comedy specials), miniseries, and documentaries and films. Netflix's original productions also include continuations of previously canceled series from other networks, as well as licensing or co-producing content from international broadcasters for exclusive broadcast in other territories, which is also branded in those regions as Netflix original content. Netflix previously produced content through Red Envelope Entertainment.</:p>
<:p>Netflix's first self-commissioned original content series "House of Cards" was released in 2013, and the company has dramatically grown its original content since that time. All programming, which is in English unless stated otherwise, is organized by its primary genre or format, and sorted by premiere date.</:p>
<:p>These shows had their original production commissioned by Netflix, or had additional seasons commissioned by Netflix.</:p>
<:p>These shows are created by Netflix and are spoken entirely or almost entirely in a non-English language. Some have the option of watching with English dub.</:p>
<:p>These original programs are documentaries that have been put into a series format, with the potential for multiple seasons, and are broken down into episodes.</:p>
<:p>These shows have been commissioned by Netflix in cooperation with a partner from another country.</:p>
<:p>These shows have been picked up by Netflix for additional seasons after having aired previous seasons on another network.</:p>
<:p>These shows are one-time original events related to original content or standalone one-time events categorized as TV shows.</:p>
<:p>The following projects have all been announced as being in development, but do not have a specific release date known at this time.</:p>
<:p>These television shows, even though Netflix lists them as Netflix originals, are shows that have been aired in different countries, and Netflix has bought exclusive distribution rights to stream them in other various countries. They may be available on Netflix in their home territory and other markets where Netflix does not have the first run license, without the Netflix Original label, some time after their first-run airing on their original broadcaster.</:p>
<:p>- Netflix Originals current list on Netflix (based on geolocation)</:p>