<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>List of TCP and UDP port numbers</:h1>
<:p>This is a list of TCP and UDP port numbers used by protocols of the application layer of the Internet protocol suite for the establishment of host-to-host connectivity.</:p>
<:p>The Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) and the User Datagram Protocol (UDP) needed only one port for full-duplex, bidirectional traffic. The Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) and the Datagram Congestion Control Protocol (DCCP) also use port numbers. They usually use port numbers that match the services of the corresponding TCP or UDP implementation, if they exist.</:p>
<:p>The Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) is responsible for maintaining the official assignments of port numbers for specific uses. However, many unofficial uses of both well-known and registered port numbers occur in practice. Similarly many of the official assignments refer to protocols that were never or are no longer in common use. This article lists port numbers and their associated protocols that have experienced significant uptake.</:p>
<:p>The port numbers in the range from 0 to 1023 (0 to 2 − 1) are the "well-known ports" or "system ports". They are used by system processes that provide widely used types of network services. On Unix-like operating systems, a process must execute with superuser privileges to be able to bind a network socket to an IP address using one of the well-known ports.</:p>
<:p>The range of port numbers from 1024 to 49151 (2 to 2 + 2 − 1) are the registered ports. They are assigned by IANA for specific service upon application by a requesting entity. On most systems, registered ports can be used without superuser privileges.</:p>
<:p>The range 49152–65535 (2 + 2 to 2 − 1) contains dynamic or private ports that cannot be registered with IANA. This range is used for private or customized services, for temporary purposes, and for automatic allocation of ephemeral ports.</:p>
<:p>- Internet protocol suite</:p>
<:p>- List of IP protocol numbers</:p>
<:p>- Lists of network protocols</:p>
<:p>- Comparison of file transfer protocols</:p>