<:import macros/html.xml />
<:h1>List of web directories</:h1>
<:p>A Web directory is a listing of Web sites organized in a hierarchy or interconnected list of categories.</:p>
<:p>The following is a list of notable Web directory services.</:p>
<:p>- DOAJ.org – Directory of Open Access Journals</:p>
<:p>- Jasmine Directory - Lists websites by topic and by region.</:p>
<:p>- Sources – general subject web portal for journalists, freelance writers, editors, authors and researchers; in addition to a search engine it includes a subject-based directory.</:p>
<:p>- Starting Point Directory – Founded in 1995, relaunched in 2006, charges a fee.</:p>
<:p>- World Wide Web Virtual Library (VLIB) – oldest directory of the Web.</:p>
<:p>- Business.com – Integrated directory of knowledge resources and companies, that charges a fee for listing review and operates as a pay per click search engine.</:p>
<:p>- Hotfrog – one of the largest collections of business website directories in the World.</:p>
<:p>- Library and Archival Exhibitions on the Web – international database of online exhibitions which is a service of the Smithsonian Institution Libraries.</:p>
<:p>- ProgrammableWeb – resource on APIs that provides a directory of APIs.</:p>
<:p>- SkillsBase – Directory of skilled professionals</:p>
<:p>- Virtual Library museums pages – directory of museum websites around the world.</:p>
<:p>- 2345.com – Chinese web directory founded in 2005. The website is the second most used web directory in China.</:p>
<:p>- Alleba – Filipino search engine website, with directory.</:p>
<:p>- Timway – web portal and directory primarily serving Hong Kong.</:p>
<:p>- AboutUs.org – directory from 2005 to 2013.</:p>
<:p>- Anime Web Turnpike – was a web directory founded in August 1995 by Jay Fubler Harvey. It served as a large database of links to various anime and manga websites.</:p>
<:p>- Biographicon – directory of biographical entries.</:p>
<:p>- DMOZ (also known as Open Directory Project) – was at one point the largest directory of the Web. Its open content was mirrored at many sites. Offline since March 2017.</:p>
<:p>- Google Directory – copy of DMOZ directory, with sites listed in PageRank order within each category. Closed in July 2011.</:p>
<:p>- Internet Public Library – librarian-edited directory, product of a merger with the Librarians' Internet Index (LII) in 2010. Closed in June 2015.</:p>
<:p>- Intute – directory of websites for study and research. Maintenance stopped in July 2011, archives remain available.</:p>
<:p>- LookSmart – operated several vertical directories from 1995 to 2006.</:p>
<:p>- Lycos' TOP 5% – from 1995 until 2000 it aimed to list the Web's top 5% of Websites.</:p>
<:p>- Yahoo! Directory– first service that Yahoo! offered. Closed in December 2014.</:p>
<:p>- Yahoo! Kids – oldest online search directory for children, until its discontinuation as of April 30, 2013.</:p>
<:p>- Zeal – volunteer-built Web directory; it was introduced in 1999, acquired by LookSmart in 2000, and shut down in 2006.</:p>
<:p>- List of search engines</:p>
<:p>- 1337x – directory of torrent files and magnet links used for peer-to-peer file sharing through the BitTorrent protocol.</:p>
<:p>- Shopping directory</:p>