<!--
  ~ /*
  ~ 	Thyme is an educational game to assist teenagers in time management, and tracking.
  ~ 	Copyright (C) 2019 Theodore Preduta, Larry Yuan
  ~
  ~ 	This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
  ~ 	it under the terms of the GNU Affero General Public License as published
  ~ 	by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
  ~ 	(at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ 	This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ 	but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  ~ 	MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
  ~ 	GNU Affero General Public License for more details.
  ~
  ~ 	You should have received a copy of the GNU Affero General Public License
  ~ 	along with this program.  If not, see <https://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
  ~ */
  -->
<:import path="macros/html.xml"/>
<:h1>
Gioachino Antonio
</:h1>
<:p>
Gioachino Antonio Rossini[n 1] (Italian: [dʒoaˈkiːno anˈtɔːnjo rosˈsiːni] (About this soundlisten); 29 February 1792 –
13 November 1868) was an Italian composer who gained fame for his 39 operas, although he also wrote many songs, some
chamber music and piano pieces, and some sacred music. He set new standards for both comic and serious opera before
retiring from large-scale composition while still in his thirties, at the height of his popularity.
</:p>
<:p>
Born in Pesaro to a trumpeter father and a singer mother, Rossini began to compose by the age of 12 and was educated at
music school in Bologna. His first opera was performed in Venice in 1810 when he was 18 years old. In 1815 he was
engaged to write operas and manage theatres in Naples. In the period 1810–1823 he wrote 34 operas for the Italian stage
that were performed in Venice, Milan, Ferrara, Naples and elsewhere; this productivity necessitated an almost formulaic
approach for some components (such as overtures) and a certain amount of self-borrowing. During this period he produced
his most popular works including the comic operas L'italiana in Algeri, Il barbiere di Siviglia (known in English as The
Barber of Seville) and La Cenerentola, which brought to a peak the opera buffa tradition he inherited from masters such
as Domenico Cimarosa. He also composed opera seria works such as Otello, Tancredi and Semiramide. All of these attracted
admiration for their innovation in melody, harmonic and instrumental colour, and dramatic form. In 1824 he was
contracted by the Opéra in Paris, for which he produced an opera to celebrate the coronation of Charles X, Il viaggio a
Reims (later cannibalised for his first opera in French, Le comte Ory), revisions of two of his Italian operas, Le siège
de Corinthe and Moïse, and in 1829 his last opera, Guillaume Tell.
</:p>
<:p>
Rossini's withdrawal from opera for the last 40 years of his life has never been fully explained; contributary factors
may have been ill-health, the wealth his success had brought him, and the rise of spectacular Grand Opera under
composers such as Giacomo Meyerbeer. From the early 1830s to 1855, when he left Paris and was based in Bologna, Rossini
wrote relatively little. On his return to Paris in 1855 he became renowned for his musical salons on Saturdays,
regularly attended by musicians and the artistic and fashionable circles of Paris, for which he wrote the entertaining
pieces Péchés de vieillesse. Guests included Franz Liszt, Anton Rubinstein, Giuseppe Verdi, Meyerbeer and Joseph
Joachim. Rossini's last major composition was his Petite messe solennelle (1863). He died in Paris in 1868.
</:p>